because all of these things can happen
every cycle there are some interesting
things that we need to consider and
those are can we do the same cycle issue
of an instruction and then immediately
dispatch that instruction in the same
cycle if it doesn't need to capture any
results typically the answer here is no
why well because while issuing the
instruction we are putting stuff in its
reservation station and usually to
dispatch we need to test what's in the
reservation station so during the issue
cycle we are writing to the reservation
station and that reservation station is
not ready yet to be recognized as a
dispatchable instruction so pretty much
the reservation station is treated as
empty during this cycle while we are
dispatching the instruction and only
starting in the next cycle that
instruction becomes eligible for
dispatch
but it is possible to design the
processor in a way that allows same
cycle issue in this patch the next thing
is whether it's possible to do same
cycle capture and then dispatch so if an
instruction is sitting in a reservation
station after being issued and it
captures its last missing operand in
this cycle can it also dispatch in this
cycle typically the answer to this
question is also no and that is because
again the reservation station here
updates its status from operands missing
to operands available during the cycle
one is doing the capture and next cycle
this reservation station looks like it's
something that might dispatch but it is
again possible to capture operands and
consider this instruction for dispatch
it just needs more harder for that and
finally can we update a rat entry for
both issue and write result in the same
cycle what's happening here is that an
instruction that is being issued might
need to update the rat to change the
entry that belongs to its destination
operand meanwhile the instruction that
is broadcasting also needs to update the
rat that corresponds to its destination
operand so if the instruction that is
being issued and the one that
is writing its result have the same
register that is their destination then
this rat entry needs to be sort of
updated twice so can we do that and the
answer to this is typically yes because
this is not something where the entry
needs to be written once and then
written again what we need to ensure is
that the instruction that is issuing
ends up being the one whose value is
kept in the rat so pretty much needs to
write to the same entry in the rat the
end result of that should be the thing
that the issuing instruction wrote why
well because the right result
instruction is trying to point others
who need to read this register to the
registers that it's going to write
meanwhile the issuing instruction which
is later in the program order is telling
the instructions that are going to issue
after it that they need to look at its
reservation station for the result and
because the instructions who will read
the rat are the ones that issue even
later they need to see the latest value
of the register which means they need to
see the value that the issuing
instruction is producing and because
this is a simple decision here you just
write this one and not this one if both
need to be written we can do that in the
same cycle